Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is ה, Hey, and
we are עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah 5 and
we pick up on ד עמוד ב Dalet Amud Bet about ten
lines down where it says יום מאיטרף בעגל סימן Yom Me'itaref Ba'agal
Siman
and so that's going to be a סימן siman of the different
discussions to come, then גופא. Gufa. So at the end of the
line after the two dots, about ten lines down, and you know
here we're dealing with a lot of אגדתא Aggadata here, which in
my opinion is really here to also be
framing the issues of מסכת עבודה זרה Masechet Avodah Zarah with just
sort of how we're how we navigate a larger world around us
that is not Jewish and sometimes hostile to us and how we
sort of the theological questions that it raises for
us. So, the גויים Goyim seem to have it good, how do
we explain why we suffer so much, the attractions of that larger
world. So far we've introduced a couple of major themes. Number one,
you know, that in the future time the גויים Goyim are all
going to get punished and even their sort of for the fact
that they did not involve themselves in תורה Torah and all of
their major accomplishments, you know, building roads and conquering countries and all
of that type of thing is really not worth anything. Even their
claim that it's there to help us for תורה Torah is not
going to be given any credit. So that sort of sends the
message that A, in the end we're going to be rewarded, they
are going to be punished, so that should be reassuring to us
and B, what really really matters is תורה Torah and that theme
that, you know, the centrality of תורה Torah whether it means learning
תורה Torah or doing מצוות Mitzvos is a has been a very
major theme so far in the אגדתא Aggadata and another theme that
was touched upon that we've been focusing on recently is also the
fact about how is it that we suffer and that really in
the end the punishment against the non-Jews is going to be harsher
than the punishment for the Jews and our suffering is only ultimately,
you know, for our ultimate reward in the future time. So sort
of dealing with the types of logical either both temptations or theological
questions that happens from us being surrounded by this idolatrous pagan non-Jewish
culture and what traditional answers are to that. So now we pick
up here with גופא. Gufa. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי Amar Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi says רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
מאי דכתיב mai dechtiv what's meant by the פסוק pasuk אשר אנכי
מצוך היום לעשותם Asher Anochi Metzavcha Hayom La'asotam that I command you
today to do them? היום לעשותם ולא למחר לעשותם Hayom La'asotam Velo
Lemachar La'asotam
today is when you're supposed when to do them, it's not going
to be tomorrow, which sort of means, you know, do things now,
don't delay, but it also of course the למחר Lemachar here means
in the עתיד לבוא Atid Lavo in עולם הבא, Olam Haba, now
in this world is the time to be doing the מצוות Mitzvos
not in the world to come. היום לעשותם ולא היום ליטול שכרם
Hayom La'asotam Velo Hayom Litol Secharan
but similarly the same way you don't do מצוות Mitzvos in עולם
הבא, Olam Haba, you also עולם הבא Olam Haba is where you
get the reward not where you do מצוות. Mitzvos. So here in
this world is where you're doing the מצוות Mitzvos but not where
you're receiving the reward. So again answering this question about why is
it if we devote ourselves to תורה Torah and מצוות Mitzvos that
we do not always seem to be as successful as the pagans,
the nations around us. ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי Va'amar Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi also said רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
כל מצוות שעושין בעולם הזה באות ומעידות אותם לעולם הבא Kol Mitzvos
She'osin Ba'olam Hazeh Bo'os Umididots Osam La'olam Haba all the מצוות Mitzvos
that we do in this world are going to testify to our
righteousness, to our rightness also, you know, in the world to come.
Again even if now we are mocked or debased or whatever degraded
by the surrounding nations, in the end they will testify to our
rightness and our righteousness, the מצוות Mitzvos that we have done. שנאמר
Shene'emar as the פסוק pasuk says יתנו עדיהם ויצדקו ישמעו ויאמרו אמת
Yitnu Adeihem Veyitzdaku Yishme'u Veyomru Emet
they will give their testimony and they will be found righteous, they
will hear and they will say it is true and this of
course echoes back the פסוק pasuk that was quoted right at the
beginning of the מסכת masechet you know יום אידם, Yom Edam, עדיהם,
adeihem, testimony. So יתנו עדיהם ויצדקו Yitnu Adeihem Veyitzdaku אלו ישראל eilu
Yisrael
they will give their testimony and they will be found righteous, these
are the Jews, they will show look we've been doing a life
of תורה Torah and מצוות, Mitzvos, we are righteous. ישמעו ויאמרו אמת
Yishme'u Veyomru Emet they will hear it and they will say it
is true אלו עובדי כוכבים eilu ovdei kochavim these are the idolaters,
the non-Jews. In the end of times they will acknowledge that we
have done, you know, that we are the righteous one, we are
the ones that are deserving of reward.
Okay and or we have lived the righteous life. ואמר רבי יהושע
בן לוי Va'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi similarly says רבי יהושע בן
לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi כל מצוות שעושין בעולם הזה באות וטופחות
אותם לעולם הבא Kol Mitzvos She'osin Ba'olam Hazeh Bo'os Vetorfas Osam Letichlam
La'olam Haba all the מצוות Mitzvos we're going to do not just
are going to show that we were correct but they're going to
like slap the non-Jews, slap the non-Jews in the face, you know,
show up the non-Jews for all of the wrong things that they
have done wrong. באות וטופחות על פניהם Bo'os Vetorfas Al Pneichem slap
them in their face. שנאמר ושמרתם ועשיתם כי היא חכמתכם ובינתכם לעיני
העמים Shene'emar Ushmartem Va'asitem Ki Hi Chochmatchem Uvinatchem Le'einei Ha'amim
you shall observe them and do them because it is your wisdom
and your understanding you know the fact that you are. a wise
and understanding people in the eyes of the nations. נגד העמים לא
נאמר, Neged ha-amim lo ne'emar,
opposite the nations, it does not say, אלא לעיני, Ella l-einei, but
in their eyes. מלמד שבעט וטרפז בפניהם, Melamed she-ba'at v-tarpas bifneihem,
it's kind of like smack 'em right in their face and show
them that they were wrong and that, you know, the lives that
they have lived has been worthless and we were the ones that
were right, we are the truly wise ones. Now of course it's
a little funny because that פסוק, pasuk, כי חכמתכם ובינתכם לעיני העמים
אשר ישמעון את כל החוקים ואמרו רק עם חכם ונבון הגוי הגדול
הזה, ki chachmaschem u-vinaschem l-einei ha-amim asher yishme'un es kol hachukim v-omru
rak am chacham v-navon hagoy hagadol hazeh, it sort of makes it
sound like the מצוות mitzvos will, you know, that the non-Jews will
see in this world
that our life of מצוות mitzvos is the true one and the
one of wisdom, but the גמרא, Gemara, but also פסוקים pesukim sound
like we're going to get rewarded in this world, but the גמרא
Gemara sort of puts that all לעתיד לבוא l-asid lavo for the
future time. Okay. ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, V-amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi, also says רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, לא
עשו ישראל את העגל אלא ליתן פתחון פה לבעלי תשובה. lo asu
Yisrael es ha-egel ella litein pischon peh l-ba'alei teshuvah.
The Israelites at the time of הר סיני Har Sinai only made
the עגל egel in order that there should be an opening for
the people who need to do תשובה, teshuvah, meaning what we're going
to say is that they were at such a high level,
they were not at, it makes no sense that they worshipped the
עגל egel and the only explanation is is that sort of like
the guy who spills the wine so that all the guests shouldn't
feel upset about, you know, if they spill something. They did it.
Really question is, is he really saying this was what their motive
was or the fact that they did it, the fact that it
was allowed to happen, you know, somehow ultimately this shows people that
even if you sin and even if you were at a very
high level and you sin, there's always a way back because God
accepted, you know, their תשובה. teshuvah. שנאמר מי יתן והיה לבבם זה
להם ליראה אותי כל הימים. Shenemar mi yitein v-haya levavam zeh lahem
l-yira osi kol hayamim. Who would only give that their heart would
be like this, you know, to fear Me all these days? So
it shows that right after מתן תורה, Matan Torah, they were at
such a high level, the tremendous fear of God. How could it
be in forty days they worshipped the עגל? egel? It really must
have been that this happened just as a way of opening the
gates for בעלי תשובה. ba'alei teshuvah. It's actually funny, ליתן פתחון פה.
litein pischon peh. פתחון פה Pischon peh is normally an opening of
a mouth is something you don't want to give. You don't want
to give a פתחון פה pischon peh for the רשעים resha'im or
פתחון פה pischon peh for the אפיקורסים. apikorsim. Here פתחון פה pischon
peh is actually to give them a strengthen their, you know, resolve
or their open up the door for them to do תשובה. teshuvah.
Alright. והיינו דאמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בר יוחאי, V-hainu d-amar
Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, and that's similar to what
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says in the name of רבי שמעון בר
יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, לא דוד ראוי לאותו מעשה. lo David
ra'uy l-oso ma'aseh.
David wasn't, you know, wasn't at the level that he should, I
mean he was at such a high level, it was, it was
inexplicable that he could have sinned with בת שבע. Bas Sheva. ולא
ישראל ראויים לאותו מעשה, v-lo Yisrael re'uyim l-oso ma'aseh, and the Israelites
at the time of הר סיני, Har Sinai, inexplicable that they should
have sinned with the עגל. egel. לא דוד ראוי לאותו מעשה דכתיב,
lo David ra'uy l-oso ma'aseh d-chsiv, how do you know that's true
about דוד, David, that he was not, you know, he was at
such a high level, doesn't make any sense? ולבי חלל בקרבי. v-libi
chalal b-kirbi. My heart is like empty in me, meaning I am
free of any lust or יצר הרע. yetzer hara. ולא ישראל ראויים
לאותו מעשה דכתיב מי יתן והיה לבבם זה להם ליראה אותי כל
הימים. v-lo Yisrael re'uyim l-oso ma'aseh d-chsiv mi yitein v-haya levavam zeh
lahem l-yira osi kol hayamim.
So although they were at such a high level, God said if
only they could fear Me this way all the days. So how
could it be that דוד David sinned? How could it be that
ישראל Yisrael sinned? אלא למה עשו? ella lamma asu? Why did they
do it? Top of עמוד א. amud aleph. לומר לך שאם חטא
יחיד אומרים לו כלך אצל יחיד. l-omar lach she-im chata yachid omerim
lo k'la eitzel yachid.
If an individual does a sin, even a terrible sin, you could
say look, look at this individual who sinned, דוד המלך David HaMelech
did this terrible sin and he did תשובה, teshuvah, so the path
of תשובה teshuvah is open for you. שאם חטא יחיד אומרים לו
כלך אצל
יחיד ואם חטאו ציבור אומרים להם לכו אצל ציבור, she-im chata yachid
omerim lo k'la eitzel yachid v-im chatu tzibur omerim lahem l-chu eitzel
tzibur, go look at an entire community sinned, all of עם ישראל
Am Yisrael sinned and the path was open for them to do
תשובה, teshuvah, the path is always open. וצריכא, v-tzricha, and it needs
to have been both that it was done by an individual and
that it was done by a ציבור. tzibur. דאי אשמעינן יחיד, d-ee
ashmeynan yachid, if it had just been an individual, דוד המלך David
HaMelech sinned and now you can learn that an individual can do
תשובה teshuvah even when he falls from a great height. דאי אשמעינן
יחיד משום דלא מפרסם חטאיה. d-ee ashmeynan yachid mishum d-lo mefarsam chata'ei.
Maybe God makes that possible because it's not very, you know, it's
an individual, it's not necessarily, it was before social media and canceling
or whatever, so when one person did something wrong, it's not like
the whole world knew about it, so you know, maybe that makes
it easier for him to do תשובה teshuvah and also it's not
as much of a חילול השם, chilul Hashem, so God allows that.
אבל ציבור דמפרסם חטאיה, aval tzibur d-mefarsam chata'ei,
but if the whole, the whole nation sins, that it's, you know,
publicized, so maybe in that type of case there's such a חילול
השם chilul Hashem or whatever, and maybe it's also so difficult to
return from that. אימא לא, eima lo, maybe תשובה teshuvah would not
be available. So therefore we needed what happened with בני ישראל Bnei
Yisrael with חטא העגל. Cheit HaEgel. ואי אשמעינן ציבור, v-ee ashmeynan tzibur,
and if we had just had what happened with them with חטא
העגל. Cheit HaEgel. משום דנפישי רחמי mishum d-nafishei rachamei or some here
the גרסא זכותייהו. girsa zechutaihu. Maybe,
okay, for a whole ציבור, tzibur, you know, God has compassion on
them, or maybe their merit as an entire, you know, nation or
community is so great that God makes it possible for them to
do תשובה. teshuvah. אבל יחיד דלא אלים זכותיה, aval yachid d-lo aleem
zechutei, but one individual, his merit is not so great. אימא לא,
eima lo, maybe the path for תשובה teshuvah would not be open
for him. צריכה, Tzricha, you need both. Okay, but that's why they
said. Now again, I'm always reading this אגדתא, Agad'ta, the opening אגדתא
דמסכת עבודה זרה Agad'ta d'Masechet Avodah Zarah through the lens of what
מסכת עבודה זרה Masechet Avodah Zarah is about. So one of the
things it's about, I've been talking, is about the temptations, navigating the
larger pagan society, etc. But certainly, one of the things it's about
is the temptation of עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So maybe the, you
know, it's interesting that it's sort of saying, well you wouldn't say,
look, if עם ישראל Am Yisrael could do עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
at הר סיני, Har Sinai, you know, maybe that should be sort
of telling me something about, you know, that there's maybe something there,
you know, maybe that, that should make me question, maybe there is
some validity to it, I don't know, and saying no no no,
you don't understand, this was only to sort of show the path
for תשובה. Teshuvah. Maybe, maybe it's somewhat in conversation with that theme,
you know, the larger theme of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah here.
והיינו דרבי שמואל בר נחמני, V'hainu d'Rabbi Yishmael bar Nachmani, that's like
Rabbi Yishmael bar Nachmani says, אמר רבי יונתן, Amar Rabbi Yonatan, דאמר
מאי דכתיב, D'amar mai d'chtiv, what's meant by the פסוק, Pasuk, נאום
דוד בן ישי ונאום הגבר הוקם על, Ne'um David ben Yishai v'ne'um
hagever hukan al, says David the son of Yishai and says the
man who was raised above, נאום דוד בן ישי שהקים עולה של
תשובה, Ne'um David ben Yishai she'hekim olah shel teshuvah, what does that
mean הוקם
על, Hukan al, raised above? So הקים עולה של תשובה, Hekim olah
shel teshuvah, he lifted up the yoke of תשובה, Teshuvah, he demonstrated
that תשובה Teshuvah is possible. ואמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי
יונתן, V'amar Rabbi Yishmael bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan, כל העושה מצווה
אחת בעולם הזה, Kol ha'oseh mitzvah achat ba'olam hazeh, and now that
quoting Rabbi Yishmael, we're going to continue with that,
whoever does one מצווה Mitzvah in this world, מקדמתו והולכת לפניו לעולם
הבא, Makdimas v'holechet l'fanav l'olam haba, it will like be, you know,
heralded before him, it will proclaim his righteousness in the world to
come, when you world to come, you know,
announcing so-and-so, you know, who did this מצווה Mitzvah and who did
that מצווה. Mitzvah. So your מצוות Mitzvot will speak to your righteousness
in the world to come, so again, you know, in that, ultimately
your deeds will be rewarded, and it's also a nice image, you
know, that you will be, you know, you'll be appreciated, perceived through
all the מעשים טובים Ma'asim Tovim that you'll be doing, you'll be
heralded. מקדמתו
והולכת לפניו לעולם הבא, Makdimas v'holechet l'fanav l'olam haba, שנאמר והלך לפניך
צדקך, Shene'emar v'halach l'fanecha tzidkecha, your righteousness will go before you, וכבוד
ה' יאספך, U'kvod Hashem ya'asfecha, and the honor of God will gather
you in, so that's לעתיד לבוא. L'atid lavo. וכל העובר עבירה אחת,
V'kol ha'over aveirah achat, however, anybody who does one
עבירה, Aveirah, מלפפתו ומוליכתו ליום הדין, Melafefto u'molichto l'yom hadin, it sort
of clings to him and, you know, and drags after him for
the day of judgment. So, so it's sort of like you're trying
to shake it and you can't get it off of you, it's
like just clinging to you.
שנאמר ילפתו ארחות דרכם, Shene'emar yilfato orchot darkam, the ways of their
paths will, again, we're sort of reading like will sort of like
cling to them. רבי אליעזר אומר קשורה בו ככלב, Rabbi Eliezer omer
keshurah bo k'chelev, it runs after you like a dog, you know,
you can't get rid of it, it keeps on chasing after you.
שנאמר, Shene'emar, very, very powerful images I think, you know, ולא שמע
אליה לשכב אצלה להיות עמה, V'lo shamah eileiha lishkav etzlah lihyot imah,
Joseph did not listen to Potiphar's wife to sleep with her, to
be with her, לשכב אצלה בעולם הזה להיות עמה לעולם הבא. Lishkav
etzlah ba'olam hazeh lihyot imah l'olam haba. So it will always be,
I don't know exactly whether again ככלב K'chelev from that point, but
something that like will always be with you, you won't be able
to shake it from you. So that's both very powerful in terms
of the good deeds you do, you know, sometimes we think the
good deeds aren't appreciated, aren't seen, will they ever get rewarded? They're
going to herald before you like a king. However, the bad things
are going to cling to you as well and they're going to
be some like, you know, dirt and burden that you can't get
rid of, unless of course you do תשובה Teshuvah as we've just
been talking. Okay. אמר ריש לקיש בואו ונחזיק טובה לאבותינו, Amar Reish
Lakish bo u'nachzik tov l'avoteinu, let us go, since we're talking about
הר סיני Har Sinai and the חטא Cheit that they did at
הר סיני, Har Sinai, so, you know, and we framed it as
a, should I open up the gates for תשובה, Teshuvah, so Reish
Lakish also frames, you know, there was like a good thing that
came out of this. בואו ונחזיק טובה לאבותינו, Bo u'nachzik tov l'avoteinu,
let's, we should be very grateful to our forefathers, not אברהם יצחק
ויעקב, Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov, our predecessors, עם ישראל Am Yisrael that stood
at הר סיני. Har Sinai. שאלמלא הם לא חטאו אנו לא באנו
לעולם, She'malei heim lo chatu anu lo banu l'olam, had they not
sinned we never would have been born. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as it says,
אני אמרתי אלהים אתם ובני עליון כולכם, Ani amarti elohim atem u'vnei
elyon kulchem, I said that you would be like God, gods or
whatever, you know, and like most high like angels. So, and here
it seems like he's understanding, if you're like angels you don't have
sex, so they would never have had children, so the future generations
would not have been born. חבלתם מעשיכם, Chibbaltem ma'aseichem, however, this is
not part of the פסוק, Pasuk, this is Reish Lakish talking, you,
you know, your deeds were, you know, you ruined your actions, you,
you know, and you sinned, אכן כאדם תמותון, Achen k'adam t'mutun, and
now nebach you're going to die like a human being. Okay, so,
so it's not clear why it means that they wouldn't have had
children, but the idea you would have been like angels, presumably you
that you would not have had sex, you wouldn't have had children,
so it's because of that that we're here. So again very interesting,
trying to take this tremendous sin of the חטא העגל Cheit ha'eigel
and say actually some good stuff came out of it. One does
wonder about the danger of that type of claim, oh so even
if you do a terrible sin good things come out of it.
It's hard, I'm trying to sort of get a handle on like
what exactly is the... Educational sort of message here. You know, saying
something like that about גן עדן Gan Eden and the חטא Chet
of אדם הראשון, Adam HaRishon, that sort of makes sense. You know,
there you could sort of see the whole idea was sort of
exerting, you know, they had to sort of break away, they were
sort of like infants, like children, exercising their autonomy and ultimately that's
what's powerful about being human לדעת טוב ורע lada'at tov va'ra but
now the challenge is how do we serve God? You know, do
we want to be in the גן עדן? Gan Eden? גן עדן
Gan Eden is עולם הבא, Olam HaBa, our task is עולם הזה.
Olam HaZeh. So anyway, that sort of makes a certain degree of
sense. But anyway, interesting here that we're trying to sort of save
and or recognize the good that came out of חטא העגל. Chet
Ha'egel. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara is anyway going to question
the implication of this, which is that there would never have been,
they would never have had children. למימר Lemeimar says the גמרא, Gemara,
דאילו חטו לא הוו מולדו? de'ilu chatu lo havei moldu? Are you
saying that if they had not sinned they would not have given
birth, you know, sired children? והכתיב Vehaktiv אתם פרו ורבו? atem peru
u'revu? So
you know, when God commands
נח Noach and his children, he says be fruitful and multiply. Now
I don't know exactly how that means, I mean that was before
חטא העגל. Chet Ha'egel. So if the point is, I mean people
obviously sinned in דור נח. Dor Noach. But are you but the
point so it seems like the גמרא Gemara is understanding that the
claim was that
until חטא העגל Chet Ha'egel nobody would have died? But that's not
true either, that's not clear in the פסוקים pesukim at all. So
maybe the גמרא Gemara is understanding that the אתם פרו ורבו atem
peru u'revu is referring back, even though the פסוק pasuk is from
נח, Noach, referring back to אדם וחוה, Adam ve'Chava, that פרו ורבו.
peru u'revu. Anyway, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. עד סיני.
Ad Sinai. So the גמרא Gemara says no, that's only until הר
סיני. Har Sinai. Yes, until הר סיני Har Sinai people did have
kids, obviously. I mean again, it's all in the פסוקים pesukim that
people were having kids. So not exactly clear what the question was.
But anyway, okay, but once they got to their level of being
at הר סיני Har Sinai and you know, מי יתן והיה לבבם
זה, mi yitein vehayah levavam zeh, they were at such a high
מדרגה, madreigah, at that point they would have been like angels and
wouldn't have had kids. Okay. עד סיני. Ad Sinai. בסיני
נמי כתיב, Be'Sinai nami ketiv, but doesn't it also say by הר
סיני, Har Sinai, לכו
אמרו
להם שובו לכם לאהליכם? lechu imru lahem shuvu lachem le'ohaleichem? After מתן
תורה Matan Torah at הר סיני, Har Sinai, even before חטא העגל,
Chet Ha'egel, they, you know, go say to them go back to
your tents, which is understood by חז"ל Chazal to mean go back
and be with your wives. לשמחת עונה. Lesimchat onah. Okay, that's true,
that's a מצוה mitzvah of, you know, the marital, the joy of
marital sex. So it's interesting, the גמרא Gemara often frames עונה onah
like as a שמחה של מצוה, simcha shel mitzvah, the sense of
joy and pleasure, which is a whole other conversation. But it's saying
but that doesn't mean for the purpose of procreation. So now it's
very interesting. They could have been at the level of angels, they're
still having sex because that's important for them, you know, husband and
wife as a marriage, having nothing to do with procreation, important sort
of point there. Okay, but they're not having children. So that's also
a little bizarre. Like you understand the assumption that if you're like
angels you're elevated from the physical world, you don't eat, you don't
have sex and so on, but once we're acknowledging that they have
sex, why should being like angels mean that they don't have children?
So still not understanding it. Anyway, let's keep on going. והכתיב Vehaktiv
למען ייטב להם ולבניהם אחריהם? lema'an yitav lahem u'livneihem achareihem? So
you know, after God says מי יתן והיה לבבם זה, mi yitein
vehayah levavam zeh, it says in order that it will be good
for them and their children afterwards. So again, after מעמד הר סיני
Ma'amad Har Sinai and before חטא העגל Chet Ha'egel and you still
see that we're talking about them having children. לאותן העומדים על הר
סיני. Le'otan ha'omedim al Har Sinai. No, no, it means their children
that are alive right now that were at הר סיני. Har Sinai.
It doesn't mean that they will be born later, although אחריהם achareihem
does sort of sound like born later. But anyway,
excuse me, that's not the פסוק. pasuk. The פסוק pasuk says ולבניהם
לעולם. u'livneihem le'olam.
But anyway, so it doesn't necessarily so that's what the גמרא Gemara
is saying is that it doesn't mean necessarily the children that will
be born afterwards but the children that they have now. לאותן העומדים
על הר סיני. Le'otan ha'omedim al Har Sinai. ואמר ריש לקיש Ve'amar
Reish Lakish מאי דכתיב mai dechativ זה ספר תולדות אדם, zeh sefer
toldot Adam, this is the book of the generations of Adam or
of the humans. וכי ספר היה לו לאדם הראשון? Veki sefer hayah
lo le'Adam HaRishon? Did he actually have a book? No. מלמד שהראה
לו הקדוש ברוך הוא לאדם הראשון דור דור ודורשיו דור דור וחכמיו.
Melamed she'her'ah lo ha'Kadosh Baruch Hu le'Adam HaRishon dor dor ve'dorshav dor
dor ve'chakhamav. This is the telling or whatever God showed, you know,
אדם הראשון, Adam HaRishon, all the future generations, all the future leaders,
all the future wise people, wise men and women, דור דור ופרנסיו
dor dor u'farnassav and the, you know, the various political leaders or
communal leaders. כיון שהגיע לדורו של רבי עקיבא, Keivan shehigia ledoro shel
Rabbi Akiva, once God got to the generation of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, שמח בתורתו, samach betorato, אדם הראשון Adam HaRishon rejoiced in the
תורה Torah of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, ונתעצב במיתתו, venit'atzeiv bemitato, but
was anguished by רבי עקיבא's, Rabbi Akiva's, you know, terrible death and
martyrdom and suffering. אמר Amar he said ולי מה יקרו רעיך אל,
veli mah yakru rei'ekha El, and to me what is how dear
are your thoughts or weighty are your thoughts, O Lord, which means
like how am I supposed to comprehend again how רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva suffered such a terrible death. ואמר רבי יוסי, Ve'amar Rabbi Yossi,
okay, so number one that shows every generation, right? through רבי עקיבא
*Rebbi Akiva* and so on, so even at the time of אדם
הראשון Adam Harishon *Adam HaRishon* it was
foreseen that there would be all these future generations it was never
part of the plan that there should not be future generations. ואמר
רבי יוסי אין בן דוד בא עד שיכלו כל הנשמות שבגוף *V'amar
Rebbi Yosi Ein Ben David ba ad sheyichlu kol haneshamot shebaguf*. Also
saying what was part of the plan, רבי יוסי *Rebbi Yosi* says
that the משיח *Mashiach* won't come until all of the souls that
God has stored up in heaven in the warehouse which is called
the גוף *guf* for some reason, the body which stores the
souls. So every time a baby is born one of those souls
gets distributed and משיח *Mashiach* won't come until all of those souls
are used up. שנאמר *Shene'emar* as the פסוק posuk *pasuk* says כי
לא לעולם אריב *ki lo l'olam ariv* I will not fight forever
ולא לנצח אקצוף *v'lo netzach ektzof* I won't be angry forever meaning
in terms of the sin and this world eventually משיח *Mashiach* come
כי רוח מלפני יעטוף *ki ruach milfanai yaatof* a spirit from me
will יעטוף *yaatof*, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says means like is holding back,
the spirits are holding it back ונשמות אני עשיתי *uneshamot ani asiti*
because of the of the souls that I have created once those
souls are used up then will come the time of משיח *Mashiach*.
So anyway you see that it was never part of the plan
that there should not be future generations. So how can ריש לקיש
*Reish Lakish* say that we would not have come into this world
had they not sinned at הר סיני Har Sinai, *Har Sinai*? So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לא תימא אנו לא באנו לעולם *lo
teima anu lo banu l'olama*, it's fine. ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* didn't
mean we never would have been born אלא אימא *ela eima* what
he really meant to say לא באנו אלא *lo banu ela* what
he meant to say was כמי שלא באנו לעולם *k'mi shelo banu
l'olam*. It would be as if we weren't born meaning the again
they would be like angels they would have lived forever. So if
that generation would have been forever then what value would we have
had? Now of course presumably if the first generation would have lived
forever the other generations would have also lived forever and the whole
point of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here is that there would have
been later generations but maybe it's sort of saying if the older
generation is never going to die out then the younger generation never
feels that they're getting their chance. So because so if had they
not sinned it would have been
like our lives would have been considered like nothing or again maybe
we're assuming that only that generation that stood at הר סיני *Har
Sinai* would have lived forever other
generations would not. But anyway it would have been like we would
never have been born. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says למימרא דאי
לא חטאו לא הוו מייתי *l'meimra de'ee lo chatu lo havi maysei*?
Are you telling me that had they not sinned they would not
have died? והכתיב *v'chasiv* פרשת יבמות *parshas yevamos* ופרשת נחלות *u'parshas nachalos*?
But the תורה Torah *Torah* talks about about the act of יבום
*yibbum* and the and who inherits so clearly now of course that's
after הר סיני *Har Sinai* and after חטא העגל *cheit ha'eigel* that
those פרשיות *parshas* are written but this is sort of assuming that
it was all already given before חטא העגל *cheit ha'eigel* and therefore
so you see it was already part of the plan that they
were going to die. Now again from there it makes it sound
like not it didn't just mean that that generation would have died
it means it makes it sound like none of the generations would
have died if the later generations would have that would have been
the obvious answer it was needed for the other generations. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is assuming now if it weren't for חטא העגל
*cheit ha'eigel* no generations would have died but then the younger generations
would have been nothing compared to the older ones. Again not exactly
clear why if everybody is living forever but okay. Anyway so how
do you explain the fact if nobody was going to die that
it says פרשת יבמות *parshas yevamos* and פרשת נחלות *parshas nachalos*? So
על תנאי *al tnai*. No it means in
case you happen to sin and you no longer live at the
stay at this level of living forever then here are going to
be the הלכות halachot *halachos*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ומי
כתיב קרא על תנאי *u'michsiv kra al tnai*? Would those פסוקים *pesukim*
have been written on condition stipulation? Again the פסוקים *pesukim* were not
only written after חטא העגל *cheit ha'eigel*
but okay. It was all the תורה Torah *Torah* that
preexisted before the world was created. אין *in* yes דהכי אמר ריש
בן לקיש *dehachi amar Reish ben Lakish* this is what ריש בן
לקיש *Reish ben Lakish* says מאי דכתיב Mai de'chtiv, ויהי ערב ויהי
בוקר יום הששי *mai de'chsiv v'yehi erev v'yehi voker yom hashishi*? It
was the day sixth, day the sixth. מלמד שהתנה הקדוש ברוך הוא
עם מעשה בראשית *Melamed shehisten hakadosh baruch hu im maaseh bereshis* God
stipulated with the all of the acts of creation ואמר אם im
מקבלים ישראל Yisrael, את התורה מוטב *v'amar im mekablim Yisrael es hatorah
mutav* if the Israelites accept the תורה Torah *Torah* good ואם לאו
אחזיר אתכם לתוהו ובוהו *v'im lav achazir eschem l'tohu vavohu* if not
I'll return everything to void and nothingness. Now again that actually is
about that the world is a is sort of is conditional or
that the תורה Torah *Torah* won't necessarily be given to the world
if the world is not deserving of it. It's not exactly the
same as this idea like whether a particular מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* will
ever will ever be applied because will there ever be people that
will die that this מצוה *mitzvah* will be relevant but okay it's
somewhat similar. If there's not if the world's being destroyed there aren't
people to do the מצוות mitzvot. *mitzvos*. The תורה Torah *Torah* still
exists whether they're going to be those conditions in the world but
again it's here the ideal situation is that they don't sin and
people live forever and then there's no need for פרשת נחלות *parshas
nachalos* and פרשת יבמות *parshas yevamos*. But anyway this is what now
we have reinterpreted ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*. to say that if they
wouldn't have sinned they would have lived forever, it would have been
like we never would have been born. Ah, there are מצות that
assume death, okay that's in the possibility that they did sin which
ultimately is what happened. Okay, מיתיבי meiseivi says the גמרא Gemara, I'll
challenge this assertion that they wouldn't have died. מי יתן והיה לבבם
זה mi yitein vehaya levavam zeh who would only give like that
because ultimately this is the פסוק posuk that we're going back to,
right if only their hearts would have been like this which is
what we cited before to say why you can't even understand why
they sinned.
So
at that moment though they were at such a high level, so
the ברייתא braisa says look, even when they were at that level
it was not possible that they would have destroyed, you know, nullified
the מלאך המות, malach hamaves, the angel of death, that they would
have conquered death even at the level that they were at. Why?
שכבר נגזרה גזרה shekvar nigzira gzeira it was already decreed from the
time of אדם הראשון that people are going to die. So that
was never in the cards. הלא קיבלו ישראל את התורה אלא כדי
שלא תהא אומה ולשון שולטת בהן, halo kibelu Yisrael es haTorah ela
kedei shelo tehei uma velashon sholetes bahen, but had they again the
funny it sort of goes back to the motivation they only accepted
the תורה Torah. for the purpose of, but what it really means
is not that that's why they accepted the תורה Torah but their
level that they achieved at accepting the תורה Torah. would have accomplished
that no nation ever would have subjugated them had they not sinned
afterwards. Okay where were we? הלא קיבלו ישראל את התורה אלא כדי
שלא תהא אומה ולשון שולטת בהן. halo kibelu Yisrael es haTorah ela
kedei shelo tehei uma velashon sholetes bahen. שנאמר למען ייטב להם ולבניהם
לעולם shene'emar lema'an yitav lahem ulevineihem le'olam that it should be good
for them and their children forever. So the way it's good forever
is that they are totally not subjugated. So anyway so you see
it says it's impossible to conquer the angel of death? So even
at מעמד הר סיני Ma'amad Har Sinai it was never going to
be that they would have lived forever? No, so the גמרא Gemara
says הוא דאמר כי האי תנא hu de'amar ki hai tanna like
the following תנא tanna that actually says no, at that moment they
did conquer the angel of death. דתניא רבי יוסי אומר, detanya Rabi
Yosei omer, Rabbi Yosei says לא קיבלו ישראל את התורה אלא כדי
שלא יהא מלאך המות שולט בהן. lo kibelu Yisrael es haTorah ela
kedei shelo yehei malach hamaves sholet bahen. Again at the moment that
they accepted the תורה Torah they were at the level again it
sounds like they only did it for the sake of, but what
it really means is at the moment they accepted the תורה Torah,
they were at the level that the angel of death had no
control over them. שנאמר אני אמרתי אלוהים אתם shene'emar ani amarti elohim
atem going back to the פסוק posuk, that Reish Lakish quoted, I
said you were like gods, ובני עליון כולכם uvenei elyon kulchem you
were like angels, but חבלתם מעשיכם chavaltem ma'aseichem you corrupted your deeds,
אכן כאדם תמותון achen k'Adam temutun and therefore again the חבלתם מעשיכם
chavaltem ma'aseichem is inserted into the פסוק, posuk, therefore you will die.
So again אכן כאדם תמותון. achen k'Adam temutun. And we should have
pointed out that once the גמרא Gemara moved away from Reish Lakish
meaning that they never would have had children, לנו לא בנו לעולם
lanu lo banu le'olam literally, to say no they would have lived
forever, you know that is does sound like exactly the פסוק, posuk
I thought you would be most high and you would be beyond
death, but נבך nebach now you are going to die. רבי יוסי
נמי הא כתיב למען ייטב להם ולבניהם לעולם Rabi Yosei nami ha
kesiv lema'an yitav lahem ulevineihem le'olam but Rabbi Yosei doesn't he who
says that they would conquer death doesn't say in order that it
would be good for them, which seems to be like, you know,
a normal life but a good life which is not being subjugated?
So the גמרא Gemara. gives the obvious answer. No, טוב הוא דהוה
המיתה איכא. tov hu dehavah hamisa ika.
So I'm sorry it's still part of the question. So it'll be
good but they'll still die? So רבי יוסי אמר לך, Rabi Yosei
amar lach, so he could say to you, no, כיון דליכא מיתה
אין לך טוב גדול מזו, keivan deleika misa ein lach tov gadol
mizo, says it'll be good for them, what means to be good
for them is the most extreme good which is that they would
not die. So that's what would have happened had they not sinned.
ותנא קמא הא כתיב אכן כאדם תמותון veTanna Kamma ha kesiv achen
k'Adam temutun what does the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma do with the
פסוק passuk that says נבך nebach now you're going to die which
sounds like had you not sinned you would not have died? מאי
מיתה עניות. mai misa aniyus.
No it doesn't literally mean now you'll die because you always would
have died. It means now you'll suffer experiences that will be like
death. Had you not sinned you would have been, nobody would have
subjugated you, you would have only had a good life. Now you
will
suffer, be subject to experiences that will be like death. מאי מיתה
עניות. mai misa aniyus. And one of them is poverty. דאמר מר
de'amar mar as the master has taught, ארבעה חשובים כמת arba'a chashuvim
k'mes there are four that are considered like dead. אלו
הן elu hen and these are they, עני ani a poor person,
סומא suma a blind man,
מצורע metzora somebody who has צרעת, tzara'as, ומי שאין לו בנים umi
she'ein lo vanim and somebody who does not have kids. עני דכתיב
כי מתו כל האנשים ani d'kesiv ki mesu kol ha'anashim for all
the people who were seeking you Moshe have died. ומאן נינהו u'man
ninhu and who were those people? דתן ואבירם, Doson va'Aviram, they're Doson
and Aviram, we just that's again just חז"ל's's Chazal take on this.
ומי
מתו והא הוו u'mi mesu veha havu did they really die?
We know that they were alive because in the end Doson and
Aviram, you know, rebel against Moshe. Okay,
אלא שירדו מנכסיהם ela sheyardu minechaseihem but it must mean that at
that time they were poor and they had lost their wealth. Of
course it seems later that they regained their wealth, but therefore it's
as if they had died because they had lost their influence.
The גמרא gemara is I think the way to understand this because
these are harsh statements. What, somebody that's poor is like they're dead?
But I think it's talking sometimes about certain societal realities that often
the reality is that people that don't have standing, that don't have
status, that don't have wealth, that don't have standing in society, people
don't pay them attention, it could be like as if they don't
exist if they're not given any value within society. And hopefully we
don't only value people because of that, but that does sometimes happen.
סומא דכתיב במחשכים הושיבני, Suma dikhtiv bemakhshakhim hoshivani, סומא, suma, the פסוק
Pasuk, says you have caused me to go in darkness, כמתי עולם,
kemetei olam, like the dead of the world. Okay, and again, obviously,
people that are blind are very, very capable, even in the time
of the גמרא, gemara many of the great אמוראים Amoraim were blind,
רב יוסף Rav Yosef was blind and so on. But again, but
maybe it could be understanding first of all, it could be a
projection from a sighted person's perspective that feels like if you weren't,
for sighted people, sight is our primary way of getting information about
the world. So it seems like it would be like I'd be
dead if I could not have access to sight, so that might
be the perspective of a sighted person. It also again might be
sort of saying from society's perspective maybe you are devalued under
these cases. Again, not that that's a good thing, but that's sometimes
a reality.
מצורע, metzora, somebody with leprosy, and they're clearly somebody that's banished from
society, דכתיב אל נא תהי כמת, dikhtiv al na tehi kemet, let
our sister not be like dead, we just read that in the
תורה. Torah ומי שאין לו בנים, umi she-ein lo banim, so it
shows you that leprosy is like death, דכתיב הבה לי בנים ואם
אין מתה אנכי, dikhtiv havah li banim ve-im ayin metah anokhi, give
me children and if not I will be dead. So sometimes again
that's maybe something
different in terms of a woman's experience. Could be that also sometimes
we're very focused on infertility for the woman, it also can be
really tragic for the man, but for the woman, the ability to
bear children, to become pregnant, and if not able to do that
could really seem like something particularly in
the past societies, but for many people even today could be seen
like a fundamental, like not being able to do a core function,
a core part of what of what it means to be a
person. So that could be sort of being like dead. And also
sadly, in society sometimes and sometimes also in Orthodox societies and Jewish
communities, somebody that doesn't have children is also seen as more marginal.
These of course are not good things, these are things that we
really have to work on addressing continually, all of this to the
degree that these are societal realities. Anyway, so that's what it would
have meant. It would have meant that I would have been like
dead but not literally dead had you, outside, now that you have
sinned, you will suffer experiences that could be experienced like death. Okay,
תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, the rabbis taught, אם בחקתי תלכו, im be-hukkotai
telekhu, אין אם אלא לשון תחנונים, ein im ela lashon takhnunim,
if you listen to my edicts, אם means like please, it's like
משה Moshe is begging them please just keep the מצוות. mitzvot, וכן
הוא אומר לו עמי שומע
לי,
vekhen hu omer
lu ammi shome'a li, oh, if only my people would listen to
me, God, משה Moshe is begging them to do the מצוות, mitzvot,
כמעט אויביהם אכניע, kim'at oyeveihem akhni'a, then I would subjugate their enemies.
ואומר לו הקשבת למצותי, ve-omer lu hikshavta le-mitzvotai, if only you would
have listened to my מצוות, mitzvot. ויהי כנהר שלומך, vayehi khannahar shelomekha,
then your peace would be flowing like a river, ויהי
כחול זרעך וצאצאי מעיך, vayehi khahol zar'akha vetze'etza'ei me'eikha, etc. תנו רבנן,
tanu rabbanan,
back to הר סיני, מי יתן והיה לבבם זה להם, mi yitten
vehayah levavam zeh lahem, if only their hearts would be like this,
if only they would be open to at this level of fearing
God and of doing the מצוות. Mitzvot, אמר להם משה לישראל, amar
lahem Moshe le-Yisrael, משה Moshe said to ישראל, Yisrael, כפויי טובה בני
כפויי
טובה, kefuyyei tovah benei kefuyyei tovah, ingrates, children of ingrates. בשעה שאמר
הקדוש ברוך הוא לישראל, besha'ah she-amar Ha-Kadosh Barukh Hu le-Yisrael,
when God said to ישראל, Yisrael. מי יתן והיה לבבם זה להם,
mi yitten vehayah levavam zeh lahem, if only their hearts would be
like this, היה להם לומר, hayah lahem lomar,
they or you should have said, תן אתה, ten attah, God, yes,
we want it, give it to us. God was opening the door,
he said if only they would be at this level forever. משה
Moshe said you didn't see the goodness that was right in front
of your eyes, that was the perfect opportunity to say God please
give it to us, allow us to be at this level. It's
only because you're ingrates and you don't appreciate the good things that
you were seeing that you did not see that opening that God
was giving you at that moment. Okay so now the גמרא gemara
is very powerful. Now the גמרא gemara is going to unpack that.
כפויי טובה דכתיב, kefuyyei tovah dikhtiv, now what does he mean ingrates,
meaning from some other experience we know that you're ingrates because it
says this was because משה Moshe said מי יתן והיה לבבם זה
להם, mi yitten vehayah levavam zeh lahem,
he frames it this way at the end of forty years when
he's talking about מעמד הר סיני. Ma'amad Har Sinai. At this stage
משה Moshe says I've already learned that you're ingrates, דכתיב ונפשנו קצה
בלחם הקלוקל, dikhtiv venafshenu katzah balekhem hakkalokel, our soul is disgusted with
this thin bread. this light bread. They're talking about the מן Man
and the way רש״י Rashi explains it, it was like this thing
that it did not actually, you know, lead to them to have
to defecate. There was no waste product of it. But they thought
like, oh, it's unnatural. And God is like, I'm trying to do
this to give you a blessing. You don't appreciate the goodness, you
think that it's a punishment when it's really this tremendous blessing that
God has given you. Okay, בני כפויי טובה, Bnei kfuyei tovah, and
you're also the descendant of ingrates, דכתיב De'chtiv האישה אשר נתת עמדי
היא נתנה לי מן העץ ואוכל. Ha'ishah asher natata imadi hi natna
li min ha'etz v'ochel. Adam said, you know, oh this woman you
gave me, it's all her fault, she gave me from the tree.
You're rejecting this tremendous goodness that God has given you. You don't
appreciate the goodness and you make it something bad. So here too,
God, you are at such a high level and God said, oh
if only you would be like this. And instead you said, no,
no, no, we can't. You, משה, Moshe, you be the intercessor for
us, rather than seeing this amazing opportunity God was offering you. Okay,
אף משה רבינו לא רמזם לישראל אלא לאחר ארבעים שנה. Af Moshe
Rabbeinu lo rimzam l'Yisrael ela l'achar arba'im shanah. You know what, even
משה Moshe didn't hint to them this idea that they should have
seized this opportunity. He waited 40 years. It was only in דברים
Devarim when retelling the story of מעמד הר סיני Ma'amad Har Sinai
did he frame it this way. אלא לאחר ארבעים שנה שנאמר ואולך
אתכם במדבר ארבעים שנה וכתיב ולא נתן ה׳ לכם לב לדעת ועיניים
לראות ואזניים לשמוע עד היום הזה. Ela l'achar arba'im shanah shene'emar va'olech
et'chem bamidbar arba'im shanah u'chtiv v'lo natan Hashem lachem lev lada'at v'einayim
lirot v'oznayim lishmo'a ad hayom hazeh.
Now 40 years later, you know, now you're at a level where
you should be able to understand, but you know what this opportunity
that you had that you wasted. וכתיב. U'chtiv. Okay, אמר רבה שמע
מינה, Amar Rabbah shma mina, from this we can infer, לא קאי
איניש אדעתיה דרביה עד ארבעים שנין. Lo ka'i inish ada'teih d'rabbeih ad
arba'im shanin.
People don't truly understand their master until 40 years later. Now who's,
who's the person who's the master? רש״י Rashi says it means even
משה Moshe didn't understand the tremendous opportunity, the way the door was
being opened there, you know, until 40 years later. And that's why
משה Moshe waited 40 years, until 40 years later משה Moshe understood
what God meant. God was dropping a hint, you know, and, and
משה Moshe finally understood it 40 years later and he told it
over to ישראל. Israel, Others say no, no, no, it means בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael didn't understand what God meant until 40 years later.
בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael didn't understand. משה Moshe knew they wouldn't be
able to appreciate this. It would take for 40 years, you know,
until 40, finally 40 years later they would finally able to appreciate
what that experience meant and then משה Moshe was able to give
them תוכחה Tochacha about it. Okay, אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan,
said רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan משום רבי בנאה, Mishum Rabbi Banna'ah, מאי
דכתיב, what's meant by the פסוק, אשריכם זורעי על כל מים משלחי
רגל השור והחמור, Ashreichem zorei al kol mayim m'shalchei regel hashor v'hachamor,
praised are you those who spread their seed over all waters, who
send out the leg of the ox and the donkey. אשריהם ישראל,
Ashreihem Yisrael, praised is ישראל, Yisrael בזמן שעוסקים בתורה ובגמילות חסדים, Bizman
she'oskim baTorah u'vigmilut chasadim, when they learn תורה Torah and do
גמילות חסד. Gemilut chesed.
יצרם מסור בידם, Yitzram masur beyadam, their יצר הרע Yetzer hara is
given over into their hands. So again, this is, you know, the
theme here about at the time of מעמד הר סיני, Ma'amad Har
Sinai, you were at such a tremendous level, you should, if you
could only stay at this level and so on. So once again
and also the theme about the central importance of תורה. Torah, If
you're learning תורה Torah. and מצוות, you will have total control over
the יצר הרע. Yetzer hara. ואין הם מסורים ביד יצרם, V'ein hem
mesurim beyad yitzram, and the יצר Yetzer won't have control over you.
Because and again I would sort of try to tie it into
the theme of the מסכת, Masechet, a lot of this מסכת Masechet
is again the temptations of the larger non-Jewish society, you know, we
can do that through making תקנות, Takanot, you know, don't drink their
wine and, you know, don't, you know, don't have this interaction with
them and so on. But also the real thing that's going to
protect you from all of those things is תורה ומצוות. Torah u'mitzvot.
That will mean that your יצר הרע Yetzer hara will be מסור
בידך. Masur beyadecha. תורה וגמילות חסדים. Torah u'gmilut chasadim. ואין הם מסורים
ביד יצרם. V'ein hem mesurim beyad yitzram. שנאמר אשריכם. Shene'emar ashreichem. בזמן
ש-. Bizman she-. ואין זריעה אלא צדקה. V'ein zri'ah ela tzedakah.
To spread the seed is righteousness, which means גמילות חסדים. Gmilut chasadim.
שנאמר זרעו לכם לצדקה וקצרו לפי חסד. Shene'emar zir'u lachem l'tzedakah v'kitzru
l'fi chesed. Plant for you for righteousness and harvest for חסד. Chesed.
So that's גמילות חסדים. Gmilut chasadim. ואין מים אלא תורה, V'ein mayim
ela Torah, and מים Mayim is תורה, Torah שנאמר הוי כל צמא
לכו למים. Shene'emar hoy kol tzamei l'chu lamayim. So that if you're
doing תורה and גמילות חסדים, Gmilut chasadim, משלחי רגל השור והחמור. M'shalchei
regel hashor v'hachamor. So,
so then what does that mean? תנא דבי אליהו לעולם ישים אדם
עצמו דברי תורה כשור לעול וכחמור למשאוי. Tana d'vei Eliyahu l'olam yasim
adam atzmo divrei Torah k'shor l'ol u'chachamor l'masoy. You should make yourself
to the words of תורה like an ox for the yoke. You
know, you should, you know, you like break your sort of יצר
Yetzer and and subjugate yourself to, to the dedication of תורה, and
like a donkey for the for the burden, like you should be
willing to really carry the heavy, you know, the burden of תורה.
And if you devote yourself to that then the יצר הרע Yetzer
hara is מסור בידך. Masur beyadecha.
Okay.
So that is the end of that major opening אגדתא Agadata for
the גמרא. Gemara Okay. By the way משלחי רגל M'shalchei regel רש״י
Rashi says this last point about what do you call it, about
תנא דבי אליהו Tana d'vei Eliyahu is not the. End of the
previous point. רש״י Rashi says the משלח רגל meshaleiach regel is, רש״י
Rashi says: משלחין ומשליכין רגלי יצר הרע מעל אדם מאליהם. mishalchin u-mashlichin
raglei yetzer hara me'al adam me'alehem.
Okay,
so they're cast away the visiting of the יצר הרע. yetzer hara.
That was sort of the first רש״י Rashi and the second point
about בתנא דבי אליהו ba-Tana D'vei Eliyahu was a similar point but
not the idea of יצר הרע מסור בידך, yetzer hara masur beyadcha,
but just in general you have to really dedicate yourself to תורה
like an ox and a dog. Okay, גמל ימים gimel yamim finally
back to the משנה, mishna, back to the הלכה halachic discussion. So
we can't do business with them three days before their holidays. Why?
Presumably because they'll be rejoicing and happy that they had this good
fortune. They bought what they wanted, they sold what they wanted, they
paid up their loan, they collected their loan, and they'll bring that
joy to their worship of עבודה זרה. avoda zara. But the גמרא
Gemara is going to focus not on just that it'll be a
joyous interaction, but if you buy and sell with them they might
be able to buy the items that they need for their עבודה
זרה avoda zara practice. And this is an
inherent ambiguity in the משנה mishna or you
know between the various גמרות, gemarot, there's really not consistency about whether
the concern is this sort of joy that they'll have and then
it applies to a wide range of transactions or is it much
more specific about using something for their עבודה זרה avoda zara rituals
and therefore a narrower range of activities or maybe it fundamentally starts
with concern for rituals but then the type of a broadens to
apply to all transactions. The גמרא Gemara here is going to focus
in on the use for rituals. So let's take a look. ומי
בעינן כולי האי? u-mi be'inan kulei hai?
But do they really need three days to buy stuff, you know,
will they really buy things three days in advance for their rituals?
Do you need that much time for their עבודה זרה avoda zara
holiday? והתנן? ve-ha-tenan? We taught in the משנה: mishna: בארבעה פרקים בשנה
המוכר בהמה לחברו צריך להודיעו. be-arba'ah perakim ba-shanah ha-mocher behemah le-chavero tzarich
le-hodi'o. At four times in the year, if somebody is selling an
animal to somebody, he has to inform him: אמי מכרתי לשחוט בתי
מכרתי לשחוט imi macharti lishchot biti macharti lishchot that you should be
aware that I also today I sold this animal's mother or this
animal's daughter because there's an איסור issur אותו ואת בנו לא תשחטו
ביום אחד oto ve-et beno lo tishchatu beyom echad and it doesn't
mean that only you can't שחט shecht both the mother and the
daughter. By the way it says אותו oto but we say it
means the mother because we know who the mother is we don't
know who the father is. But it means if somebody else שחט
shechted the mother or the child, you can't שחט shecht the other
one. The person who is the one to have made it that
both of them were שחט shechted on the same day is the
one that transgresses. So if somebody is selling you an animal and
he sold the mother or the child today, he has to tell
you so that you don't because the first person who bought it
was free to שחט shecht it but you have to be aware
it's probably being שחט shechted today the other one and you can't
שחט shecht you know the one that you just bought until you
know until later. So what are those four times a year assuming
that somebody is going to שחט shecht it right away?
So ואלו הן ve-elu hen and these are they: ערב יום טוב
האחרון של חג erev Yom Tov ha-acharon shel chag so last day
of סוכות. Sukkot. תוספות Tosafot says why not the first day of
סוכות? Sukkot? Because the first day of סוכות Sukkot is you know
everybody's busy with their סוכה sukkah and their לולב lulav so they're
not necessarily spending all their time making a big יום טוב Yom
Tov meal. Also since שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret has its own identity
but it could sort of get you know sort of lost in
the in סוכות Sukkot they really wanted to make it a day
of particular שמחה. simcha. So שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret. ערב יום טוב
הראשון
של פסח erev Yom
Tov ha-rishon shel Pesach so the right before you know the first
day of פסח Pesach because you want to have a nice meal
for the beginning of יום טוב. Yom Tov. וערב עצרת ve-erev Atzeret
and before שבועות. Shavuot. So there you got סוכות, Sukkot, פסח Pesach
and שבועות Shavuot except סוכות Sukkot's focus was on the end. וערב
ראש השנה ve-erev Rosh Hashanah and ערב ראש השנה erev Rosh Hashanah
also a חג. chag. וכדברי רבי יוסי הגלילי אף ערב יום הכיפורים
בגליל u-ke-divrei Rabbi Yose ha-Gelili af erev Yom ha-Kippurim ba-Galil and ערב
יום כיפור erev Yom Kippur in גליל Galil
because they would you know there's a מצוה to eat on ערב
יום הכיפורים. erev Yom ha-Kippurim. Anyway, so you see that people would
only even when they're having a whole big feast they're only buying
one day in advance for their feast, not three days in advance.
Of course the funny thing here is that the גמרא Gemara sort
of applies the הלכות halachos and the realities of Jewish practice and
assume it applies to non-Jews which is just like at certain level
doesn't make any sense at all. I mean you know it has
to bring this into the normal rabbinic discourse so it puts it
in conversation with these other משניות mishnayot that talk about what Jewish
practice is. But if this is really a concern here about the
non-Jews using it in their pagan rituals or their feasts then it
should just be based on what those realities are for the non-Jews.
Okay but maybe the גמרא Gemara is assuming I mean maybe the
only way I can make sense of this is that it's assuming
whatever those realities are those are realities that like vary and we
have to have strict rules like three days. I mean who knows
you know what the pagans in Rome do what do the pagans
in in Syria do what do the pagans in North Africa do?
So rather than you know we have to set a fixed time
because you know we have to standard- it would make sense that
we should maybe want to use a model that we have and
maybe, you know, model that we have in the Jewish context. Maybe
that's a way to understand it. So anyway, let's see where the
גמרא Gemara goes with it. So the גמרא Gemara says התם דאכילה,
Hasam de'achilah,
now there they want it just for their feast, סגי בחד יומא,
sagi be'chad yoma, so people will buy it just on the day
itself or the day before. הכא דהקרבה, Hacha de'hakravah, but here the
concern is not they're buying animals for their feast, they're buying animals
to offer them on sacrifices on their holidays, בעינן תלתא יומי, binan
tlata yomei, they want three days, you know, to make sure that
it doesn't have any blemishes, etc. So that's where the three days
comes from. So the גמרא Gemara says ולקרבה סגי בתלתא יומי, ul'hakravah
sagi be'tlata yomei, what,
three days is sufficient to make sure there are no blemishes? והתניא
ve'hatanya שואלין ודורשין בהלכות הפסח קודם הפסח שלשים יום sho'alin vedorshin behilchos
hapesach kodem hapesach sheloshim yom רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר שתי שבתות,
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer shetei shabbatot, you ask start discussing the
הלכות halachos thirty days before, two weeks before, and the גמרא understands
that asking about the הלכות halachos means about buying קרבנות, korbanot, you
know, animals for קרבנות, korbanot, again, not exactly clear why it's assuming
that. Anyway, let's see what the גמרא's answer is. אנן דשכיחי מומי
דפסלי אפילו בדוקין שבעין, anan de'sh'chichi mumei de'paslei afilu bidukim she'ba'ayin, for
us when we have, you know, blemishes are even tiny little things
are blemishes, even like a little cataract of the eye, so in
the animal, בעינן תלתין יומי, binan tlashin yomei, we need 30 days
to start preparing ourselves and buying the animals and checking the animals,
etc. אינהו דמחוסר אבר אית להו, inhu de'mechusar eivar it lehu, for
them it's only something is פסול pasul for a קרבן korban if
it's missing a limb. Now this is a הלכה halacha about what
the גמרא thinks for בני נח Bnei Noach who want to bring
a קרבן korban in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it's not a
problem if it has a blemish, if it's only a problem if
it's missing a limb. Again, does that have anything to do with
the actual reality of what pagans bring for their pagan sacrifices in
their pagan temples? No. But the גמרא's again applying this sort of
lens, and the only lens we have to apply is what we
know is the הלכות of בני נח Bnei Noach who want to
bring a קרבן korban in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. And for
them it is that it's only if it's missing a limb it's
a problem, not if it has a simple a small blemish. So
therefore אית להו בתלתא יומי סגי, itlehu be'tlata yomei sagi, three days
is enough. Of course you don't need three days to check for
a blemish, to check for a missing limb, you could do that
in two minutes. So I don't begin to understand this. דאמר רבי
אלעזר מניין למחוסר אבר דאסור לבני נח, de'amar Rabbi Elazar minayin lemechusar
eivar de'asur livnei Noach, how do you know בני נח Bnei Noach
can't bring an animal that's missing a limb? דכתיב ומכל החי מכל
בשר שנים מכל, dichsiv umikol hachai mikol basar shenayim mikol, etc. Okay,
so,
and רש"י Rashi at least, so we'll end for that now, and
רש"י at least tries to bridge this gap. If you look at
רש"י דאסור לבני נח, Rashi de'asur livnei Noach, he says להקריב לגבוה,
lehakriv legavoah, ודומיא דקרבנות שנהגו אבותיהם לשמים הם נוהגים בעבודה זרה שלהם.
vedumya de'korbanos shenahagu avoseihem leshamayim hem nohagim b'avodah zarah shelahem.
We're going to assume the same way it used to be for
them when they were following הלכה halacha and bringing קרבנות korbanot for
God, they have maintained this practice for their עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
Okay, but again this is a strange thing where the גמרא tries
to bring בני נח Bnei Noach or ישראל realities onto the question
of what actually is the practice in the pagan world. Okay, we
will end here.